Register of the Association for Comparative Economic Studies records
Hoover Institution Archives
Association for Comparative Economic Studies records
1962-1973
88014
Hoover Institution Archives
9 manuscript boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, minutes of meetings, conference papers and proceedings, memoranda, newsletters and other publications, and financial records relating to comparative economic studies in the United States. Includes records of one of the Association's predecessor organizations, the Association for Comparative Economics.
Association for Comparative Economic Studies (U.S.)
Association for Comparative Economics.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
American professional organization for promotion of the comparative study of economic systems. In 1972, the Association for Comparative Economics (ACE) and the Association for the Study of Soviet-Type Economies (ASTE) merged to become the Association for Comparative Economic Studies (ACES).
Scope and Content of Collection
The Association for Comparative Economic Studies Records contain correspondence, minutes of meetings, conference papers and proceedings, memoranda, newsletters and other publications, and financial records related to comparative economic studies in the United States. The collection includes records of one of the Association's predecessor organizations, the Association for Comparative Economics.
The Association for Comparative Economic Studies (ACES) provided an avenue for scholarly exchange and supported the growth of research into comparative economics. The Correspondence includes letters of Gregory Grossman, President of ACES, as well as correspondence of presidents of the predecessor organization Association for Comparative Economics (ACE).
To further its mission, the Association hosted conferences, inviting economists to speak on relevant topics. These meetings were often held in conjunction with other organizations, such as the Midwest Economics Association and the Southern Economic Association. The Conference File includes conference proceedings, correspondence, and reports documenting these meetings.
Another important aspect of the Association's work was the publication of various economic journals. The Publications File includes correspondence and drafts associated with this work, printed copies of the ACES Bulletin, which later became Comparative Economic Studies, as well as materials related to publications of predecessor organizations.
In 1972, the Association for Comparative Economics (ACE) and the Association for the Study of Soviet-Type Economies (ASTE) merged to become the Association for Comparative Economic Studies (ACES). The Office File documents this merger, the election of ACE officers, and ACE membership.
Comparative economics.; Economics--Study and teaching--United States.; Education--United States.
- Correspondence, 1962-1973
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains incoming and outgoing letters, including correspondence of presidents of the Association for Comparative Economic Studies (ACES) and its predecessor organization the Association for Comparative Economics (ACE). Arranged in two groups: Alphabetical file and Chronological file.
  - Alphabetical file
    - A, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - B, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Biven, W. Carl, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Buckingham, Walter, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Burns, Arthur R., 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - C, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Collegiate News and Views, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Colm, Gerhard, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Copps, John A., 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - D, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Dalton, George, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - E, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - F, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - G, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Grossman, Gregory, 1963-1967 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Grossman, Gregory and Robert W. Campbell, 1972 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - H, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Hagen, Everett E., 1967 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Holbik, Karel, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Hoover, Calvin B., 1964-1967 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - I, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - J, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Koefod, Paul, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - L, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - M, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - Mc, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - N, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 27)
    - O, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - P, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - R, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 30)
    - S, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - Schnitzer, Martin, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - Schweitzer, Arthur, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 1: 33)
    - T, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 34)
    - U-V, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 35)
    - W, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 36)
    - Z, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Chronological file
    - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1: 38)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 1: 39)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 2: 5-8)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 3: 4-5)
- Conference File, 1965-1972
  Includes conference proceedings and drafts of papers, correspondence, reports on conference organization, and notes on presentations related to conferences hosted by predecessor organization the Association for Comparative Economics (ACE). ACE often held conferences in conjunction with other organizations, such as the Midwest Economics Association and the Southern Economic Association. Materials from joint conferences included. Arranged chronologically by date of conference.
  - 1965 (Box-folder 3: 6-9)
  - 1966 (Box-folder 3: 10-12)
  - 1966 (cont'd.) (Box-folder 4: 1-4)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 4: 5-9)
  - 1967 (cont'd.) (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - 1968 (Box-folder 5: 3-6)
  - 1969 (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
  - 1969 (cont'd.) (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - 1969-1971 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
  - 1971 (Box-folder 6: 4-6)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Office File, 1963-1972
  Contains administrative files, including correspondence, meeting minutes, financial documents, election files, and membership files. Includes documentation on the 1972 merger of predecessor organizations Association for Comparative Economics (ACE) and Association for the Study of Soviet-Type Economies (ASTE).
  - Constitution, undated (Box-folder 6: 8-9)
  - Elections, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 6: 10-15)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, ballots, and tally sheets. Includes memorandum on election of executive committee members during the merger.
  - Executive Secretary Report, 1972 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Financial records, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 6: 17-18)
  - Financial records (cont'd.), 1966-1969 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1963, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 7: 2-3)
  - Membership, 1966-1971 (Box-folder 7: 4-32)
    Includes correspondence, membership lists, application forms, and dues schedules.
  - Membership (cont'd.), 1966-1971 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
  - Merger, 1971 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Research topics, 1968, undated (Box-folder 8: 4-5)
- Publications File, 1962-1973
  Includes correspondence, publication lists, drafts, copies of The ACES Bulletin, and publications of predecessor organizations. Arranged alphabetically by name of publication.
  - General, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 8: 6-8)
  - ACE Newsletter
    - General, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 8: 10-11)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 8: 12-14)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 8: 15-17)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 8: 18-21)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 8: 22)
    - 1969 (cont'd.) (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 9: 2-4)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 9: 5-8)
  - ACES Bulletin, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 9: 9-11)
    Includes correspondence and drafts. The ACES Bulletin was formerly The ASTE Bulletin.
  - ASTE Bulletin, 1962, 1965 (Box-folder 9: 12-13)
- Writings by Others, 1968-1971
  Includes typescripts, reprints, and printed copies of papers related to economics. Arranged alphabetically by name of author.
  - Flagg, Denis and Virginia, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 9: 14)
    Includes correspondence
  - Gregory, Paul, 1971, undated (Box-folder 9: 15-16)
  - Hocevar, Toussaint, and Warren F. Mazek, undated (Box-folder 9: 17)
  - Jonas, Paul and Hyman Sardy, 1970 (Box-folder 9: 18)
  - Lauterbach, Albert, 1969, undated (Box-folder 9: 19)
  - Polach, Jarozlav G., 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9: 20-21)
  - Prybyla, Jan S., 1970 (Box-folder 9: 22)
  - Schachter, Gustav, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 9: 23-25)
  - Schatz, Sayre, 1969 (Box-folder 9: 26)
  - Shaffer, Harry G., 1971 (Box-folder 9: 27)
  - Skeels, Jack W., 1971 (Box-folder 9: 28)
  - Stuart, Robert C., and Paul R. Gregory, 1971 (Box-folder 9: 29)
  - Taira, Koji, 1971 (Box-folder 9: 30-31)
  - Turner, Carl B., undated (Box-folder 9: 32)
  - Wharton, Clifton R., Jr., undated (Box-folder 9: 33)
  - Woroniak, Alexander, undated (Box-folder 9: 34)